okay the next talk is going to be by
Bradley Alisia and colleagues
purposefully non-standard cybernetics an
alternative to purpose-driven control
this is going to be a 1our pre-recorded
talk so thank you
enjoy hello my name is Dr Bradley Al and
on behalf of Jesse parent Morgan huff
and Anda Nelson I'm we're from the
orthogon research and education
laboratory and the cybernetics interest
group and I'm going to talk to you today
about per purposefully non-standard
cybernetics an alternative to
purpose-driven control so we start with
a question what is the definition of
behavior and this is varied throughout
history according to the behaviorist
Behavior was identified as a reflex
elicited by stimulus associations the
consequence of reinforcement and the
current motivational state if we go
forward to the cognitive ists which is
more or less the modern view they would
say that behavior is a set of internal
mental states that are responsible for
observable behaviors with gold directed
end States now it's of note that both
behaviorist and cognitivist Views
involve feedback this leads to learning
a notion of what constitutes a state and
predictive capacity so we start with
this paper Rosen blue th all in 1943
Behavior purpose and teeology published
in the philosophy of science and it's a
formative paper in the field of
cybernetics so in that paper they have
this typology of Behavioral
classifications so we're going to return
to this typology throughout the talk and
we're going to think about how we can
reorganize this typology but it
basically defines Behavior as a set of
nested things the red text Non classes
or they're basically all other things
other than the uh black thing that we'll
be talking about at each rung of this
typology so behavior is active it's
purposeful it involves feedback which
implies some sort of chology or end goal
it's also predictive which involves
extrapolation and involves an order of
prediction so you might have first order
second order or third order prediction
so to understand what teeology is and
where it comes from we start at the
Middle Ages where teeology was the end
State or the end goal of some behavioral
process was thought of as a Divine
causation we then move forward to
teeology As Natural cause a and then it
branches off into two directions and the
first was the vitalism of bergson and
evolution by natural selection made
famous by Darwin leading from Darwin's
work we had arar who talked about tonomy
which is purpose versus history and
we'll talk a little bit about that later
in the talk kind of discontinuous to
this are two different streams so the
first at the top is where behavior is
viewed as habit that's by William James
and Thorndike that leads us to the an
molec K antology of Francis CRI and
feedback is complexity which is
summarized by control theory and
dynamical systems at the bottom is our
target paper that we just talked about
these are the views of roseen blue thin
Wier and this is feedback relative to a
goal this led us to cognitive science
and reinforcement learning at least the
modern versions of this where people
talk about gold directed behavior and
variations on that in molecular biology
such as molecular
vitalism and the tame and U methodology
IES of leban janca and Ginsburg so we'll
talk about a couple papers here and
frame some of this in context so if we
think about Behavior it's it's
essentially a form of functionalism in
the first paper here Rody and Germain
they argue that functionalism is a
pre-scientific relic so they actually
argue that the whole idea of
functionalism is something that comes
from this era of divine causality
biology is not designed so why should we
expect a function and this is something
that of course maybe is assumed about
function that it comes from some sort of
design or comes from some sort of divine
intervention on the other hand toonomic
systems are defined by spatial and
temporal information and constant
iterations Over States so we do have
these toomic systems but include modern
components only select behaviors can be
defined as selection of a goal or
derived from signals from the goal so
that means that we can't necessarily
paint Behavior with a broad brush of
teeology only some behaviors may be
theological and others maybe not not all
behaviors and this includes biological
and machine behaviors are goal selecting
and while goal directed behaviors seem
to be purposeful and it may be true that
some of these behaviors that are known
as gold directed are purposeful are
there Developmental and evolutionary
antecedence so are those Place those uh
ancestral behaviors or those basil
behaviors or behaviors that occur
earlier in development are those also
purposeful and the answer may be no so
Rosen Lu at all Define behavior as any
change in an agent with respect to its
surroundings this is much broader than
the Neuroscience psychological
definition and it sets up a contrast
between all behaviors and a subset of
purposeful
behaviors so if a behavior is put under
some sort of selection or if a behavior
is selection of something in the
environment this might lead us to a
subset of voluntary behaviors which then
some of those may be purpose ful and so
purpose is actually purposeful behaviors
is actually a subset of all
behaviors to demonstrate this we see
that clocks both mechanical and
biological are not purposeful as there
is no final aspirational state
mechanical clocks can keep time and you
can set an alarm on them but that alarm
is imposed by the outside and it's not a
property of that behavior and of itself
further more biological clock runs VI a
physiological processes like a circadian
rhythm and it can be entrained by
external white but that again is not a
final aspirational
State more generally teeology requires a
signal from a goal so it's some sort of
signal from a goal that's specific to
that behavior and purposes progress to
that goal so again with our uh example
of circadian rhythms it's entrained by
light but that light itself is not a
goal it's just something that's out in
the environment and the system entrains
itself to
it we can also see this with brains in
that brains produce behavioral outputs
but the exact mechanism is hard to
pinpoint and this is the Rost and Lal
article that we saw earlier and this
asks the question signal from what to
goal so there's a signal coming from
something to a goal but it's not clear
what that is this is something one of
our co-authors Jesse parent works on
this is a frontier map for teeology and
related complexity Theory Concepts so
the data from this is drawn from the
complex world book by crck hour this is
published in
2024 and it kind of goes over three
different concepts that are interrelated
so we have tileology organized
complexity and emergence and so you can
see that our paper Rosen blue 1943 is at
the top and this is sort of the first
paper that talks about
theology in sort of a scientific and in
a a manner of
complexity and so this is the first
paper that talks about teeology is a
property of complexity and of complex
systems so a lot of papers were
influenced by Rosen Bluth this uh
tileology was inherited by Weiner's book
cybernetics and control in 194
two other papers adaptive systems in uh
by John Holland in 1962 and
organizations and complexity also in
1962 the good regulator of course in
1970 inherited this concept but it also
inherited another concept from
organizations and complexity which is
organized complexity the good regulator
then passes down this concept of
tileology to the book order and chaos in
1993 and there's a direct link between
Rosen Bluth 1943 and the tame concept of
Mike 11 in 2022 now we going back to the
concept of organized complexity this
comes from organizations and complexity
the good regulator in 1970 and the autop
poesis paper in 1974 both share this
intellectual lineage the autop polies
paper lends that organized complexity
concept to this paper on deiv in 1982
get to this book order and chaos in
1993 and then to the tame Concept in
2020 2 finally we have emergence which
starts with the paper by Anderson war is
different in 1972 inherited by the autop
poli's paper 1974 in turn inherited by
the dissipativity paper 1982 in turn
inherited by Order and Chaos 1993 so you
can see that we have not just theology
as a concept in which we've kind of
talked about already but also a number
of other related Concepts this is 11 uh
this is the tame paper and then janca
Ginsburg this is the U paper and so Lan
proposes the tame or technological
approach to mind everyone Lev's
principle here is this cognition all the
way down we can see cognition in terms
of Minds we can see cognition in terms
of molecular phenomena we can see
cognition everywhere in between and so
behaviors all those behaviors are
cognitive to some extent and as a result
we get these diverse Minds that have
these different goal directed
competencies that allow those systems to
achieve embodied agents so in Levan's
approach you know kology is a very
important concept not just for cognitive
type behaviors but behaviors that that
go all the way down to the molecular
scale and maybe even down to the quantum
scale second theology is a means to
explain why agents develop towards goals
and so you know we can look at uh agents
such as artificial agents simple
organisms like bacteria then we can see
that like teeology is a way to explain
learn how to move towards goals the next
paper is this U paper by janca at all
and in that paper they propose a concept
called unlimited associative learning
and this concept is a minimal marker for
Consciousness so in this paper they also
Champion teeology is an intrinsic
reinforcement system you have this inter
internally regulated model in service of
attaining external goal andology plays a
role in attaining goals so again in both
cases there's a strong tendency to talk
about goals the strong tendency towards
to but we might ask the question is
behavior at these different scales and
any sort of behavior that sort of
motivated towards some sort of function
ta
logical and purposeful or is it simply a
product of the history of the system so
you know we could talk about teeology
and purpose and we've kind of set this
up that you know this is something that
has kind of come out of the natural
study of behavior but sometimes you know
we don't really fully you know sometimes
we ascribe heliology and purpose to
things that maybe are just simply a
product of the history of a system first
example I want to give is the basov
jabotinsky reaction or the bz
reaction and at the lower left you can
see a image of the bz reaction and this
is a deterministic internal model that
we can model with differential equations
and we can solve those differential
equations and get interesting
solutions that produces a cave chaotic
behavioral output or the Dynamics of the
system which are sort of the unfolding
history of the system so if we take an
example of some sort of chemical soup we
can achieve bot Jaa tinsky reactions or
bz reactions by setting up this sort of
set of differential equations these
ordinary differential equations setting
up an initial condition and we get these
spiral waves and scr wings that result
and so if we have slight variations in
initial condition we end up with very
different systems very different types
of patterns in these um in these systems
and we can describe this with ODS and
one might say okay there's a purpose to
this but the purpose isn't necessarily
clear when you run this simulation again
and again with different types of
initial
conditions there's a chaotic Behavior at
a variational dynamic dynamical output
so this is an example of the tip
trajectories of BZ waves this is from a
paper I Bron an angle in
1993 and it shows how there's a lot of
variation in the pattern but there's a
sort of um you know constant aspect of
the pattern in terms of the tip
trajectories so one might say okay the
purpose is to produce these tip TR
trajectories instead of the actual
pattern and the interactions which may
be true but then of course you know
that's something something that I want
you to think about as we go through the
rest of this
talk we could also plug the bosov
jabotinsky reaction into a cybernetic
model with higher level feedbacks and so
I talk about this in this dimensions of
morphogenesis lecture on the dorm
YouTube channel and what I'm getting at
in that talk is that there different
dimensions of morphogenesis there's
onedimensional morphogenesis
two-dimensional morphogenesis
higher dimensional
morphogenesis and so you see this kind
of output and so I'm asking the question
here is this purposeful or is this a
product of sort of a a chemical a
dynamical chemical system with a history
and so we can also look at this as a
cybernetic model where we have feedbacks
and we have other sorts of
complexity and you know we can fit it
also into that behavioral uh typology of
roseen blue
okay another
uh another example is this thing called
an allostasis machine so an Al estasis
machine is is basically the output of an
internal model and so an internal model
of course as we talked about is
something that has some sort of capacity
for memory and learning and maybe some
sort of output that looks Behavioral or
cognitive in some way so what we can do
is we can take this internal model we
can have an oscillator which is a
stochastic process or a deterministic
process depending on our oscillator and
we can have a memory with
capacity so we have this oscillator that
produces an output and we have sensory
information that can drive the
oscillator
forward this output creates a trajectory
which is an interaction with between
noisy perturbations in a historical
trajectory that's shown in this red
line and the historical trajectory is
stored in the internal model was a
memory with a capacity so as this red
line unfolds there's a memory of it in
the internal model and it responds to
external perturbations which
drive
this uh Red Line in different directions
and the oscillator tries to recover to
the original state and so you get these
dynamics that may look purposeful but
really have this stochastic and adaptive
component we get more into this aspect
of dynamical control systems I look at
intrinsic motivation in dynamical
control systems so this is this tiomkin
paper PRX life and so in this paper they
talk about how you might model maybe
something like an alisasas machine as a
set of actions generated without a
specific reward signal so in this paper
they talk about that as intrinsic
motivation they model this with except
States and AST actions so an action maps
to a number of states and this results
in a trajectory forced bya observation
stochasticity this is entropy so you
produce the trajectory there's an
observation that you have and that's the
entropy of the system and so you
maximize actions that increase
susceptibility rather than entropy these
are noisy observations that we do in
perfect observational States and you can
compare par arbitrary length sequences
of such sequences in the future this
gives your internal model the ability to
sort of integrate information and to
find sort of solutions to problems the
idea is that you have the system that
can work towards a goal but it isn't
driven by any sort of teeology it's just
driven by this memory component and the
stochastic component and that's all you
need a number of other papers here that
I'm going to talk about I'm going to put
this in the framework of anticipatory
systems from our paper on tonomy and any
Tristen so to get to this we need to re
kind of reformulate our behavioral
typology so remember we talked about
behavior is having these different
components we have these non- classes so
in this case we're going from Behavior
to active Behavior a purposeful Behavior
but that's contrasted with historical or
markovian behavior then we have feedback
prediction and Order of prediction and
so ERM refined the Rosen blue that all
theological category to Parts purposeful
agentic and historical marvian so if we
go back to the Benny and friston paper
they talk about the free energy
principle is managing different forms of
gold
directedness and how you need negative
feedback to attain homeostasis there's
purpose in in cases where the goal is
known which is a marvian system and
surprisal was minimized which resolves
uncertainty then we can expect purpose
purpose isn't really just some sort of
magical thing or it's not some sort of
thing that requires is a strict goal
it's just certain conditions under which
our behavioral trajectory exists we can
also look at anticipatory systems it's
the louy paper and this anticipatory
systems come from a generative model
with depth so this is where we have
temporal aspects of the system that lead
us to teeology so it's more that the
teeology is the history of the system
and this depth comes from an internal
model so basically if we go back to the
internal model we have some process that
generates Behavior we have this memory
the memory is basically something that
stores everything that the system has
experienced and that's how we get toy to
kind of understand this a little bit
more we want to distinguish between a
marvian system and a non-markovian
system so our maravian system is where
you have inter arrival times so there's
a series of things coming in in time
this is exponentially distributed in
this diagram we have sensory information
coming in we have some sort of encoding
this encoding is a binary Channel with
noise where we have these lines that
represent some sort of sort of sensory
input or perturbation of the system and
the inner arrival times the area between
these lines so the inal arrival time is
obviously not equidistant in this
example but it's in between the red and
blue lines or the red and red lines and
so we can take those in our arrival
times and if they're exponentially
distributed we have a Marian system if
they're not then we have a non-markovian
system and so we've kind of developed
this uh distinction between markovian
and non-markovian sensory information
and how that relates to an information
measure in our gibsonian information
work so gibsonian information is a
markovian but can also be non-markovian
information processing system and the
citation is here so going back to that
behavioral typology we have active
purposeful feedback prediction and Order
of prediction feedback is everything
that is circular non-transitive this is
the present p past and future your
behavior is controlled by a margin of
error Corrections of agent location the
time te relative to a goal position or
state and so if we think about this in
terms of a feed forward process feed
forward process is where the past is
your input present is your process and
the future is your output in feedback
however it's a little bit different your
input comes in the past and then you
have this present State here and then
you have feedback which is the past and
that Loops back to your input which
means that your input is now the
future and so the future is actually
present with past feedback so you see
the loop here you have input to the
present you have this feedback which is
the past and it goes to the Future so
now you have this future State before
the present State and if that keeps
going out you get this all output with
alternative Futures so your feedback
loop can be positive or negative and in
this case it doesn't matter what we're
interested in is sort of the order of
past present and future so we end up
with this input we go to the present we
go to the past we go to the future we go
back to the present so we're sort of
interdigitating different types of
causality here instead of just having
this past present and future aspect to
things we have this sort of convoluted
aspect of past present and future if we
go back to our historical map we recall
that non olical things can be
characterized as feedback as complexity
and so there are two papers here that
talk about pit control that kind of get
us at that
idea so pit control is proportional
integral derivative
control and if we think back to our
example of chemotaxis and
phototaxis we find that PID control can
be applied to chemotaxis and other types
of biological control so this is The
Balter and Buckley paper they talk about
this in terms of a variational free
energy
minimization given a linear generative
model they talk about pit control
resembling a reflex arcate mechanism so
this is the reflex arc we find in
sensory motor control and the free
energy principle provides a more direct
account of control this is where we
don't have any hidden states in the
process of propioception so they're
focusing on
propioception and but they also talk
about chemotaxis and so they kind of
give us this sort of uh variational free
energy interpretation of
this um in go all which is a more
engineering take on this the pi and PD
components or the proportional integral
and the proportional derivative
components and directed Network
synchronization are all sort of uh
components of this control
mechanism in particular the pi and PD
components of PID Define present past
and future components in an internal
model control
system we can then also start to think
of feedback as complexity in terms of
nonlinearity and complexity as well so
this paper by Westerberg at all stimulus
history not expectation Drive sensory
prediction errors in a melean cortex
this is from the bio archive so the
author has framed this in terms of
predictive coding so predictive coding
explains cortical responses in two ways
a feed forward model where an internal
model of expected events occurs or in
terms of an internal model of expected
events or a feedforward approach and a
calculation of prediction error for
unexpected stimuli or feedback approach
the latter are actually Global oddballs
which defy expectations in a local
context so in Mouse and macak which are
their two model organisms they see two
types of signal they see a normal
response where the internal model is
matched by little stimuli and a global
Oddball response which is emerged which
emerges as a higher order response to
this normal response we also can look at
this nonlinearity in terms of Behavioral
output in general and then burstiness or
nonnormality of so this paper burstiness
of human physical activities and their
characterization and quantifying
postural sway Dynamics using burstiness
and interent time distributions kind of
gets at both this aspect of Marian
systems and and a behavioral system that
exhibits sort of nonlinear complexity
both papers focus on the burstiness of
postural sway in postural sway we have
this Paradigm where someone stands on a
plate and that plate is a force plate
that measures the center mass of the
individual and then we can measure this
and we get this nice dynamical
trajectory that has different features
that we can analyze so it's a behavioral
output that exhibits a lot of nonlinear
characteristics and dynamical
characteristics
teuchi and Sano focuses on burstiness
and postural sway in terms of adult
housework and children's play behaviors
they studied physical activities of
children between ages two and five and
they found that burstiness is not an
acquired feature it's something that's
inate burstiness is present in healthy
healthy individuals not in people with
movement disorders or impairments they
also looked at inter event time
distributions and Associated
fluctuations so we talked about inner
event times as being key to more Marian
and non- Marian systems they found that
they're bursty so they're these
stochastic signals that have a noise
component and sometimes this is in
function of someone trying to maintain
their balance and sometimes it's just
noise that's generated by the nervous
system that's added to the stochastic
signal in both cases This Is Not Gold
directed it's generated by physiological
system it's a very complex behavioral
signal and it's not explainable by
either a pan or gausian model which
means that it has this very complex set
of features so if we do some
experimental cybernetics on this we can
find that if we have the right internal
model we can produce very interesting
output signals or behavioral signals
some of these T kind of look like they
could be chological but they're not this
is just simply running some stochastic
sign one example is just a pure
stochastic signal the other one is
having a stochastic signal with feedback
that then takes that signal and
integrates it at a later date so what we
have here are two Fe forward processing
one is a spway stochastic signal in Blue
on the left and then the other is a sum
signal that is STO a stochastic delay of
that signal or the signal on the right
so on the right we have the blue signal
you can kind of see it under the red
signal so the red signal is the one
that's bursty and it's is basically
where at random intervals we sum
previous output and we add it to the
present output so we end up with these
bursts and so the delay which is this uh
sum signal that we uh that represent our
bursts is the buildup of the input
signal it produces these bursts or what
we might call avalanches and so we can
see that we can produce these nonlinear
signals from a simple internal model so
this is the classic coopel paper from
1982 it actually has a couple of
interesting things to say of cybernetic
oriented things so we have this feed
forward which is where you have a
process that goes from A to B to C to
D and we also have these systems that
have strong back coupling so we have a
process that goes from A to B to C to D
then we have these back couplings from D
to C C to b b to a and so what's more
likely to be the case of like you know
actual sort of complex behavior is not
the feed forward signal but the strong
back coupling this is where we have
ubiquitous feedback Str back coupling
can be intractable to analysis but
produces the most interesting aspect of
network interactions and strong back
coupling produces things like Collective
Behavior emergent properties stochastic
outputs and nonlinear outputs or
Avalanches which we saw in our
experimental cybernetics a few slides
back we can think about feedback and we
talked about this relationship between
past present and future a few slides
back and we also talked about maybe some
of these types of behaviors that are
non-random but maybe structured in a
certain way and we can think about
feedback just sort to revisit the idea
of feedback that roseen blue F all gave
us which is that feedback was purposeful
so we can ask the question is feedback
purposeful or simply non- random and so
we can think of past present and future
relationships as a trip around the
feedback Bove namely that we can take
our input we can take the present and
have a feedback loop that gives us past
information into a new present when we
get a new time point and that ends up
giving us a future that can then be
recycled so this has implic ations for
prediction we can go past present future
to prediction or we can have inputs that
produce these sort of differently
ordered past present Futures and use
that as the output so feedback
mechanisms reorder processes systems
with a lot of feedback aren't teeology
per se maybe they produce outputs that
look te but they're not theological and
so going back to the different orders of
prediction which were kind of like the
final output of our Behavioral
um typ typology what are the different
orders of prediction well we have our
first second third and fourth or higher
order feedback so we can have these
feedbacks that have PR past present
future but we can Nest them together so
that we can
have a past of a past of a past
contributing to the present or to the
Future and so that's really interesting
because what it's suggesting is these
higher level feedbacks maybe AR also not
te logical but there's some sort of
memory or maybe there's some sort of um
you know intervent interval and the way
it's structured so there's some
structural aspect of feedback that might
be really interesting that isn't
chological per se but it given some of
these other examples might have some
structural significance so if we build a
a cybernetic model that is really kind
of complex and has a lot of interlocked
feedbacks and things like that we can
get some really interesting
results so our different types of higher
order feedback you know we can kind of
think of these in terms of the
derivatives of position so the
derivatives of position revisiting that
from undergraduate physics you have
velocity acceleration jerk snap crackle
pop and these are just where you start
with velocity and you get a a derivative
of velocity which is acceleration you
get a derivative of acceleration which
is jerk and so on and these can be
thought of in this way of having these
higher order feedbacks or these
reordering is a past present future to
give you these really complex Dynamics
in cases of derivatives of position and
feedback feedback if it goes farther
into the past the effects persist
farther into the future so if we go back
a couple of feedback loops nested on top
of one another and we introduce that to
the new present or the new future those
effects persist further into the future
so we get these really
long-term effects in a dynamical system
instead of just being
local how does this translate into the
neuroc corelates of behavior well we go
back to our idea about Behavior sort of
being natural teally
logical and we have to think about like
kind of how we kind of assume that
behavior does magic things so if we get
a behavior like this with higher order
feedbacks it tends to resemble the sort
of magical aspect it could be something
like emergence it could be something
like burstiness or something like a set
of avalanches that occur and so these
are things that you know you know give
us really interesting Dynamics but are
no more sort of magical orological than
any other kind of behavior and so more
fully connect systems are perspective or
might be sentient or conscious that's
sort of the idea of does magic things so
you know we don't want to us Mis
attribute sentience or Consciousness to
something that isn't and of course this
is something that we've have a problem
with with modern AI systems that people
think they're sentient conscious when in
fact they just have this higher order
feedback and this sort of um you know
behavior that isn't necessarily what
people think it is magic things or you
know what we talk about like complexity
results from embodied function a good
example of this is kinematic chains
which we'll talk about in a little bit
but now we introduced this concept of
convolutional Cy cybernetic
architectures or ccas and so we go back
to our behavioral typology and we ask
the question can we better understand
the role of purpose or meaning and
feedback or temporal order so here we
have active Behavior purposeful Behavior
theological Behavior and the non-
classes of those are nonpurposeful the
random behavior and non-feedback or non
phological Behavior respectively but
we're going to reorder this behavioral
classification where now we have non-
prediction leading to the order of
complexity rather than prediction
leading to the order of prediction so we
start off with behavior that's active
instead of passive then we have
nonpurposeful or random Behavior instead
of purposeful and non nonactive or
passive and purpose for know non-
classes then we have feedback which is
non-teleological versus feedback which
is theological theological feedback is
now the non-class non-teleological
feedback is now the path to the order of
complexity and then instead of
prediction being extrapolation we'll
have non- prediction which is also
extrapolation and then we have our order
of complexity first second and third
order so the more feedback we have the
more complexity we have so this is an
example of a convolutional cybernetic
architecture we basically have this toy
example where we have an input and an
output the input is 0000 0 the output is
111 and we have these boxes which
process the present to the Future and
then our feedbacks uh give us like some
past date and it feeds it back to the
future or the present so we have a
ubiquitous feedback here we have some
feed forward elements we have elements
of feedback that do certain things to
the sequence and the question we ask
here is what is the maximal number of
steps needed to transform the sequence
from 0 0 0 to one11 so we start with z00
Z we put that in we kind of move to our
feedback loop our feedback loop does
certain things to the sequence and then
we end up with 111 and we actually want
to know what the maximal number of steps
is because we want to know you know how
far we can go through these different uh
feedback loops and get our answer this
can also be restated in terms of
temporal phases past present and future
so we also have more explicitly this
input of the present we have the future
as an output and then we have these
different uh Loops that give us the P
give us past information and again we're
interested in
getting the most diverse information
possible and so this is again this
maximal Loop that we're looking for so
we're trying to get the most variety out
of these uh convolutional cybernetic
architectures instead of trying to find
the most efficient path or the tightest
path or the most go directed path we can
further understand this or restate this
in terms of semantic components so we
can talk about this in terms of symbols
reference and understanding symbol being
the input reference being the feedback
or part of the feedback loop and then
understanding being the output and so we
want to accumulate as many reference as
possible for a symbol so that we get an
output of understanding and again it's
the variety that counts not optimizing
the process or trying to find a goal
directed aspect to this so if we think
about how these ccas are assembled uh we
can look at the different components of
feedback and then we can start to
assemble these more complex
structures so let's look at first order
feedback so CCA has
input and in this case we're looking at
past present future and maybe
alternative Futures and things like that
and they all produce a predictive output
so first order feedback would be an
input going to a future going to the
present and naturally the future is just
like the present plus the past the
present comes in as in
it's passed to this feedback which is
the past the present and past are added
to the Future and then the output is
some sort of predictive input so again
we have this reordering of past present
future in the first order
feedback if we have a feed forward only
case we have input which leads the
present which leads to some complex
output but of course as a feed forward
only system we just only get the benefit
of having the present we don't get to
talk about the past in the future it's
just like every input results in a an
output and that output then is complex
output within any context then if we put
together a larger set of feedback loops
we can see this sort of convolved mixed
feedback where we have first order
feedback second order feedback and a
feed forward component so these are all
different components producing two
different complex outputs so we have an
input that gives us the present we get a
first order feedback
that gives us some past and we add those
together to a future state that produces
complex output we can also have a feed
forward part of that where the input
goes to the present and then the present
isn't part of that state and then we
might have a a a second order feedback
where we have an input which is the
present it passes A first order feed
Loop uh feedback loop to the past and
another first order or second order
feedback grp to the past and those can
both be combined into the present which
is then informing a future state which
involves a longer memory which has more
information and that gives us another
complex output but we also have this
path from the second order feedback up
to an alternative future which then gets
passed out as a complex output so you
see what we have here is we have an
input it goes to the present we Sub sub
reference the past we sub reference the
past again and that gives us an
alternative future so this happens for
every cycle so you end up with these
three different types of complex
output and given this topology we can
end up with these different types of
characterizations of the system remember
again with this convolution what we're
introducing is this variety which is
actually a concept from
uh the ever good regulator theorem and a
lot of the work of w ashb so we're
dealing with producing the maximum
amount of variety so we you know we need
variety to control systems so this is
actually overall the appearance of
purposes replaced with an ensemble of
positive and negative feedback elements
with diffuse effects so remember that we
need to have not only a single closed
loop feedback but we need to have
multiple feedbacks and maybe some openlp
feedbacks in there so we can have uh
maximize a variety so the imperatives of
such a network are to gain processes or
to maximize the number of processes and
this leads us to maximizing
variety and of course variety was a
concept that was introduced by WR Ashby
in the ever good regulator theorem and
he talked about how variety is necessary
for control
but it also creates the conditions for
adaptability modularity and
modifiability so we have systems that
are both not purposeful but they also
have this sort of imperative for control
but also for other types
of conditions in a in a system that
allow it to adapt be modular and be
modifiable and so we can also add in
polarity we can have different typ YP of
effects resulting from feedback as we
talked about if we reorder past present
and future that's all well and good but
this also has relevance to different
types of processes that result in
systems so in in complex systems we have
these different effects like Avalanches
runaway feedbacks and dampened feedback
these are non-linearities and we saw an
example of avalanches earlier in our
experimental cybernetics and and that
can result from a number of feedbacks of
different polarity and this can produce
unpredictable inst stability we can have
things like runaway feedbacks which are
basically just the product of positive
feedback and that can lead to mass and
stability and we can also have something
like dampened feedback which is a
negative overly negative feedback which
sometimes makes things more controllable
and so we can have these effects that
result from these processes that have a
polarity that lead to these different
complex systems phenomena that then lead
to things that are maybe look they look
te logical or purposeful but they're
actually just the products of complexity
and so if we kind of go back and look at
like how we can model things like
connectionist learning and reinforcement
learning with cybernetics we can
actually take the equations of
connectionism and reinforcement learning
and put them into this sort of
cybernetic system system so this is
where you know we want to
take modern learning systems or
artificial learning systems and
understand them
using cybernetic approaches and maybe
apply them into these kind of
ccas and so this this is congruent with
hopefield and Sutton's alternative
Viewpoint which is that the weights of a
network are reinforced by the activity
and selection of previous inputs
so this is where we have we're looking
at Q learning here we're looking at
connectionist learning and we're looking
at sort of the ways equations are
structured and we're thinking about how
you know we can get learning from these
systems of equations and you know this
is a dynamical system you know as much
as a learning system so we want to
understand kind of how this is how this
works and so we started a random set of
weights and lack structure due to
selection we started a random set of
weights and lack of structure due to
selection we proceed to a structured set
of weights and optimal policies
unwittingly we kind of move from a
markovian system to a non-markovian
deterministic
system and so there's a tri question
here which is how do we go from
something that does not resemble purpose
to something that is purposeful the
answer is is that purposes a post talk
determination so we can model this as
habits with weights so we have this
input we have these outputs and we have
this uh CCA that's that has polarity and
we can have habits that are the serve as
the inputs and the weights are the
polarity and we have non-ic behavior in
a directed graph so this directed graph
kind of moves towards the end points the
outputs and so the lesson here is that
purpose is basically whatever we
determine these outputs to be so when we
observe a behavior a behavior is
generated by the CCA
graphs we interpret the output the way
we'd like to interpret it and as I said
before we can have these different
outputs that are that look purposeful or
they look peely logical but that's just
really a post talk
determination and we move to wier's
Alternative Viewpoint so Wier is more of
a cybernetics guy he also has an
alternative
Viewpoint and his Viewpoint focuses on
communication and information which have
both a control layer and a semantic
layer so again we have to go back to the
past present and future formulation so
instead of thinking about this in terms
of polarity we want to think about this
in terms of not just the control but the
semantics as well and so we have this
past present and future we have an input
which is the past
we have a future which is the present
with past feedback we have the present
so the present goes to the Past goes to
the future but the future also moves to
a present where there's a present with
past and future components and then an
output so if we run this in time if we
run this as a dynamical system we end up
with this the present being sort of you
know it's not really additive but it's
basically concatenating things onto the
present with information from the past
and you're informing a future trajectory
and you're you can actually generate
alternate futures of a system from this
and so this there's a control layer a
semantic layer and this gives us
information about the system both in
terms of contingencies and synergies so
connectivity and ordering provides both
contingencies
which is that nodes depend on other
nodes and synergies for nodes working
together so in this model we can't knock
out any one node and have the system
work we can't knock out the the feedback
and have this sort of
Rich self- reference we can only have
you know a feedforward model and we've
seen that that's much less
interesting we also can't knock out the
future and we can't knock out the
present we have to connect continue with
all of our
nodes but also these nodes working
together produce the synergestic
um trajectory that gives us rich
information about time it gives us this
present it gives us a a future but it
also gives these intermediate states
where we get past feedback and we get
integration of
those this stands in contrast to the
imperative of purpose and
heliology is cybernetic control and beh
or purposeful or stochastic activity
tempered by recursively recombined
temporal ordering and so this is again
one of the
ccas and a CCA is also a series of steps
that add recursive functionality so
sometimes if we think about this in
terms of our internal model memory this
is memory with sub referential power so
what allows us to have a memory again
where we can reference the past of a
past of a past and it informs the future
of the present
and adding present into future and
things like that this creates a
hierarchical system and high degrees of
intentional order so again we can add
these things together or we can run
these ccas and we can
produce this memory with sub referential
power and the output can look very
organized and hierarchical but the thing
that produced that output is not
necessarily ordered and it's not
necessarily uh there's no overarching
goal or any other sort of information
going into it so once again thinking
about habit and purposeful Behavior we
have this paper creatures of habit the
Neuroscience of habit and purposeful
Behavior this was published in
biological Psychiatry so this is where
they talk about animal behaviors being
composed of Habitual and gold directed
categories habitual is non-teleological
go gold directed is theological they
provide this sort of breakdown where you
have theological versus nonta logical
behaviors and deterministic versus
stochastic Behavior if we think about ta
logical and deterministic behaviors we
get gold directed behaviors those are
things like reaching for a Target or
moving towards a goal but of course we
know that some of these types of
goal-seeking
behaviors are chemo like chemotaxis or
phototaxis are stochastic and so if we
have teleological and stochasticity we
might have something like chemotaxis or
phototaxis we have something it's non-
chological and deterministic we have
habitual work so we have something
that's habitual it's not moving towards
a goal but it's
deterministic something like uh
scratching or like a reflex you have
nonic on stochastic behavior however we
know that that looks something like a
random walk so we can actually
characterize these different behaviors
in this way the problem with chemotaxis
and I put a question Mark in the table
so chemotaxis for example which is a
movement along chemical gradient we
already established that that was not t
logical the goal directedness in that
case is due to the environment not the
internal model and so we can look to Gib
sonian information or we can look
towards sort of thinking about why it's
not te ological and so but it doesn't
also doesn't resemble a random walk so
that provides us with a problem which is
where does this fit into this typology
so a clue to kind of where chemotaxis
and phototaxis fits into that
typology comes from this paper brain
like neurodynamics for Behavioral
control develop the reinforcement
learning and this is from the bioarchive
from this year cotal at all test two
scenarios supervised or extent and
reinforcement or developmental learning
so we have extent and developmental
learning only reinforcement learning
produces gold directed behavior and
neuroactivity similar to biology it
provides robust short-term behavioral
adaptations to
perturbations and it produces an
emergent emergence of policies that are
not purposeful in and of themselves but
lead to things that look the part so
this is reminiscent of our ccas it's
also reminiscent of our to our
discussion of chemotaxis and phototaxis
building a CCA from a small Motif is a
form of purposelessness or
purposelessness reinforcement learning
build up you build up to function and
sometimes useless structures and that's
okay another example of nonpurposeful
behavior that kind of fits into our CCA
model comes from feudal substrate Cycles
in Biochemistry and so this is the paper
stochastic amplif amplification and
signaling enzymatic feudal Cycles their
noise induced by stability with
oscillations this is from
pnas so this is where we describe these
feudal Cycles is these feedback loops
where you have an input of energy
there's entic
reaction and you get nothing that comes
out except entropy or heat so you
basically don't have an output your
output is entropy it's heat and of
course this is a problem because we
expect there to be an output we expect
this reaction to actually do something
and in fact it's creating heat but it
seems like that's a lot of work for just
heat so we have a biochemical pathway
which is a Clos feed back it does
thermodynamic work for no
reason heat is produced from an
energetic input but we don't get any
biochemical
products and this seems like it's a
waste of energy that has no
purpose but it's actually important for
regulation and other processes it
produces complex higherorder Dynamics or
amplification effects throughout a
greater biochemical system so if we go
from convolution to order we can see
that the evolution of cybernetic control
is a causal recursive chain of
contingencies and so here we look at the
contingencies in a CCA we go from one to
two to three and then that's a feed
forward system and then we can go from 1
to two to three prime to four which
feeds back to two and gives us this
output four prime or we can go from 1 to
two to 3 to four or 1 to two to three
prime to four to 5 to 6 to 7 which is an
output so we have these different
outputs from these different numbered
boxes and we have these uh resulting
processes so let's take three prime as
an example three prime is dependent on
two and one and once feedback is
operational four and five so four and
five actually do feedback to three prime
which of course is a dependency so if
you knock that dependency out you lose
your entire functionality of that part
of the
network seven on the other hand which is
another output at the top is dependent
upon 6 54 3 Prime 2 and one there's no
feedback from
delay so you can see the different types
of order and how there's a lot of
recursive chains that lead to
contingencies so again if we think about
our feudal cycle our feudal cycle is
like something at the bottom I her or
feedack back is like something at the
top of this diagram and our alternate
outputs alternate outputs are at the
right and they are of course maximizing
for variety and so if we think about the
evolution of cybernetic control as a
causal recursive chain of contingencies
we can think about the kinematic chain
which is where we have these
dependencies so D is affected by the
activities of ab and C we get this chain
it's this is this robotic arm that
extends out across two joints and the
activity in D with kinematic is
constrained by A and C and so we can
describe it in that way if we go back to
these kinds of
contingencies we know that seven is
constrained by its intermediates and
thus it is with the kinematic
chain in in the kinematic chain we can
do this in a linear fashion we can add
on conditionals as convoluted cyber as
the convoluted cybernetic Network
evolves this restricts the system to a
determin istic path behaviorally this
leads to interesting consequences for
developing sensory motor Loop and a
kinematic chain is basically sensory
motor physics with
contingency so here are examples of a
kinematic chain in
robotics and we can think
about uh embodied robotics here where we
have these control systems for these
cmatic chains maybe the CCA where we
have different types of morphologies and
we can design them appropriately we can
design and we can design them
appropriately we can design
behaviors that aren't
purposeful aren't te logical but still
give us behaviors that we can that look
intelligent we can also think about
purposeful behavior and fore cognition
so our approach to purposeful Behavior
can be applied to Fore cognition so we
have these different types of cognition
some of them being embodied some of them
being embedded some of them being
extended which means outside the brain
and some of them being inactive if we
put this in the framework of Rosen blue
th all's behavioral classification does
for Fore Force us to rethink that
behavioral classification as we did in a
number of instances in this talk now
there's one Insight of 4E that's
interesting to us which is that the
morphology environment of a system is
more important than its internal model
so we've been talking about internal
models
and how these ccas model the internal
state of behavior and how that shows
that in a lot of cases Theology and
purpose are sort of
elery but if morphology and environment
are more important than the internal
model then maybe we need to incorporate
our
ccas uh or or recast our ccas in terms
of morphology and environment as well as
an internal state in fact our CCA do
that to some extent but it's uh sort of
a a way to put this behavioral
classification on its head and so in the
case of 4E purpose is not ascribed to a
mind feedback is diffuse and complex
prediction its highest orders are not
theological they must be open-ended we
talk about this in a paper from 2023 and
Royal Society interface Focus so what is
behavior and what are its properties
so yeah we we're kind of revisiting what
Rosen Bluth talked about we're looking
at a number of examples from
neuroscience and from psychology and
from other areas animal behavior
Robotics and we kind of break down kind
of what we're looking at here so
Behavior can be intentionality it can be
goal directed and supervised and so
these are things like control systems
par cognition
and of course some of those are go
directed some of those are regulated
complexity then we have Rich higher
order complex Dynamics and those are
things like Bey reactions which we
talked about an embryogenesis which we
didn't really talk about but also
qualifies in that category so these are
D outputs of dynamical
systems we also have connectivity and
convolution which are things like
connectionism avalanches and open-ended
learning and then finally we have
behaviors that are hardwired but
recursive so with our ccas we were
modeling some Hardware behaviors in a
recursive fashion we also talked about
this in terms of non-markovian systems
and habitual Behavior we want to go
beyond the standard of te logical and
purposeful Behavior so a standard way of
thinking about behavioral regulation is
that inputs are deterministic and
outputs or Collective output should be
close-ended so if we expand the basic Lo
Loop feedback model we get an
interconnected network of retrocausal
ordering so this is something that we're
seeing in the CCA where we talk about
the order of causality past present
future we have this basic loand feedback
model but if we expand that out we get
much richer retrocausal ordering which
leads to of course to variety but it
also leads to these interesting
paradoxes and interesting effects of
higher order
feedback behavior is often open-ended
and this can be characterized by
embodied
Dynamics unpredictable which can be
characterized by a chaotic Dynamics
nonnormal which can be characterized by
non-markovian behaviors and systems
Avalanches of different types power law
Dynamics and so forth and
variational which means that it's
characterized by multiple goals and
redundancies and so this requires a
reassessment Rosen blue theal
typology and has wider consequences for
the practice of active
inference thank you for your
attention uh one of our co-authors Jesse
parent uh produced a lengthy blog post
on the Rosen blue that all paper talks
about its enduring insights and its con
uh its context in
cybernetics and then we have two papers
we talked about in the talk from our
group that stasis
machines and a primer on Gibson need
information so I thank you for your
attention
e for